var jsonData = [
    {
    "question": "Which Indian state is the largest producer in the world of the golden coloured 'Muga' silk ? ",
        "a": "Assam",
        "b": "Orissa",
        "c": "West Bengal",
        "d":"Karnataka",
    "answer": "Assam"
}, {
    "question": "Which Indian freedom fighter was popularly called 'Mahamana' ? ",
        "a":"Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "b":"Jai Prakash Narain",
        "c":"Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
        "d":"Madan Mohan Malaviya",
    "answer": "Madan Mohan Malaviya"
},
{
    "question" : "Stapes, the smallest and the lightest bone in human body, is the part of which organ ? ",
        "a":"Ear",
        "b":"Hand",
        "c":"Foot",
        "d":"Lungs",
    
    "answer": "Ear"
},
{
    
    "a":"Zinc",
    "b":"Lignite",
"c":"Copper",
    "d":"Gold"
,
"question": "Which mineral is mined at Jayamkondam in Tamil Nadu ? ",
"answer": "Lignite"
},
{

    "question": "Which Indian State would you be if you were watching birds at Ranganathittu Birds Sanctuary ,situated on as island in the kaveri river ?",
    "a":"Karnataka",
    "b":"Maharashtra",
    "c":"Tamil Nadu",
    "d":"Andhra Pradesh",
    
    "answer": "Karnataka"
    },{
    "question": "'Anandmath','Durgeshnondini', and 'kapalkundala', novels were authored by which Bengali writer?",
    "a": "Rabindranath Tagore",
    "b": "Sharat chandra chatterjee",
    "c": "Bankim chandra chatterjee",
    "d": "Bibhuti Bhushan bandopadhyay",
    "answer": "Bankim chandra chatterjee"
    },{
    "question": "Baglihar Dam,also known as Baglihar Hydroelectric Power Project, in Jammu Khasmir is built across which river ?",
    "a": "Beas",
    "b": "Chenab",
    "c": "Jhelum",
    "d": "Sutlej",
     "answer": "Chenab"
    },{
    "question": "Where was the first Indian Institute of Management (IIM) established in 1961?",
    "a":"Kolkata",
    "b":"Bengaluru",
    "c": "Ahmedabad",
    "d":"Lucknow",
    "answer": "Kolkata"
    },{
    "question":"What line connects the points on a map that receive equal amounts of rainfall ?",
    "a":"Isobar",
    "b":"Isohel",
    "c":"Isotherm",
    "d":"Isohyet",
    "answer": "Isohyet"
    },{
    "question":"On 28 May 2008, the Indian Air Force attained the Airborne Warning And Control System(AWACS)capability by procuring the Phalcon radar (mounted on Russian plane IL-76) From which country ?",
    "a":"France",
    "b":"Israel",
    "c":"Russia",
    "d":"Germany",
    "answer": "Israel"
    },{
    "question":"Which India born physicist invented the 'Optical Fibre' ?",
    "a":"C.V Raman",
    "b":"Satyendra Nath Bose",
    "c": "Homi J. Bhabha",
    "d":"Narinder Singh Kapany",
    "answer": "Narinder Singh Kapany"
    },{
    "question":"Which Australian state was formerly known as \"van Diemen's land\"?",
    "a":"Victoria",
    "b":"Queensland",
    "c":"Tasmania",
    "d":"New South Wales",
    "answer":"Tasmania"
    },{
    "question":"'Marasmus' and 'kwashiorkor' diseases are caused due to deficiency of which nutrient?",
    "a":"sodium",
    "b":"protein",
    "c":"Iodine",
    "d":"vitamin D",
    "answer":"protein"
    },{
    "question":"Which among the following is the largest Buddhist monastery in India?",
    "a":"Ghum monastery(West Bengal)",
    "b":"Rumtek monastery(Sikkim)",
    "c":"Twang monastery(Arunachal Pradesh)",
    "d":"Kursha monastery(Jammu Kashmir)",
    "answer":"Twang monastery(Arunachal Pradesh)"
    },{
    "question":"According to 2001 cencus which state has the highest literacy rate?",
    "a":"Goa",
    "b":"Mizorzm",
    "c":"Tripura",
    "d":"Kerala",
    "answer":"Kerala"
    },{
    "question": "'Ace', 'Double fault', 'Smash', Second service', and 'Game point' terms are related with which sport ?",
    "a":"Tennis",
    "b": "Squash",
    "c":"Table Tennis",
    "d":"Badminton",
    "answer":"Tennis"
    },{
     "question": "Where is the Lal Bahadur Shastri National Academy of Administration, the apex training institution for senior members of the civil services in India, located ?",
    "a":"Mussoorie (Uttarakhand)",
     "b":"Mount Abu (Rajasthan)",
     "c": "Darjeeling (West Bengal)",
     "d":"Kodaikanal (Tamil Nadu)",
    "answer":"Mussoorie (Uttarakhand)"
    },{
     "question": "Which among the following grassland region is also known as the \"World's Breadbasket\" ?",
    "a":"Pampas of Argentina",
    "b":"Prairies of North America",
    "c":"Savannas of Africa",
    "d":"Steppes of Russia",
    "answer":"Prairies of North America"
    },{
     "question": "Which ancient Indian sage authored the 'Yog Darshan' ?",
    "a": "Jaimini",
    "b": "Gautam",
    "c":  "Kapil Muni",
    "d":  "Patanjali",
    "answer": "Patanjali"
    },{
     "question": "Which Asian city was formerly known as 'Batavia' ?",
    "a": "Yangon (Myanmar)",
    "b":  "Hanoi (Vietnam)",
    "c":  "Jakarta (Indonesia)",
    "d":  "Beijing (China)",
    "answer": "Jakarta (Indonesia)"
    },{
     "question": "Which seventh century Indian mathematician was the first in the world to treat 'zero' as a number and show its mathematical operations ?",
    "a":  "Aryabhatta",
    "b":  "Medhatithi",
    "c": "Brahmagupta",
    "d":  "Bhaskaracharya",
    "answer":"Brahmagupta"
    },{
     "question": "Which city houses the headquarters of International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), the world's 'Atoms for Peace' organisation set up in 1957 within the United Nations family ?",
    "a": "Tokyo (Japan)",
    "b":  "Vienna (Austria)",
    "c":  "Geneva (Switzerland)",
    "d":  "New York (USA)",
    "answer":"Vienna (Austria)"
    },{
      "question": "Which was the only session of Indian National Congress (INC) presided over by Mahatma Gandhi ? ",
    "a":"Surat (1907)",
    "b": "Belgaum (1924)",
    "c": "Lahore (1929)",
    "d":  "Tripuri (1939)",
    "answer":"Belgaum (1924)"
    },{
      "question": "Which state is the largest producer of tobacco ? ",
    "a": "Karnataka",
    "b":  "Madhya Pradesh",
    "c":  "Maharashtra",
    "d":  "Andhra Pradesh",
    "answer": "Andhra Pradesh"
    },{
     "question": "For Border-Gavaskar Trophy, the Indian cricket team plays against which country ? ",
    "a":  "England",
    "b":  "New Zealand",
     "c":  "Australia",
    "d":  "South Africa",
    "answer": "Australia"
    },{
      "question": "On account of its numerous temples, which city is also known as the 'Cathedral City of India' ? ",
     "a":  "Madurai (Tamil Nadu)",
      "b":  "Haridwar (Uttarakhand)",
     "c": "Bhubaneswar (Orissa)",
     "d": "Varanasi (Uttar Pradesh)",
    "answer":"Bhubaneswar (Orissa)"
    },{
      "question": "Which Indian state does not have any scheduled tribe community ? ",
    "a":"Sikkim",
    "b":  "Haryana",
    "c": "Gujarat",
    "d": "Tamil Nadu",
    "answer":"Haryana"
    },{
     "question": "Baku is the capital city of which country ? ",
    "a":"Azerbaijan",
    "b": "Kazakhstan",
    "c": "Kyrgyzstan",
    "d":  "Uzbekistan",
    "answer":"Azerbaijan"
    },{
     "question": "Which Indian region is the only place in the world where the Asiatic Wild Ass is found ? ",
    "a":  "Sunderban",
    "b":  "Leh and Ladakh",
    " c":  "Coromandel",
    "d":  "Rann of Kachchh",
    "answer": "Rann of Kachchh"
    },{
     "question": "Which Ramon Magsaysay award winner founded the 'Asha for Education', a secular organisation dedicated to bring socio-economic change in India by focusing on basic education ? ",
    "a":  "Sandeep Pandey",
    "b":  "Lakshmi Chand Jain",
    "c":   "Pandurang Shastri Athavale",
    "d":   "Mahesh Chandra Mehta",
    "answer":"Sandeep Pandey"
    },{
      "question": "In which city would you come across 'Deeksha Bhoomi', where Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar had embraced Buddhism along with thousand of his Dalit followers on 14 October 1956 ? ",
    "a": "Bodh Gaya (Bihar)",
    "b":  "Sarnath (Uttar Pradesh)",
    "c":  "Kushinagar (Uttar Pradesh)",
    "d":  "Nagpur (Maharashtra)",
    "answer": "Nagpur (Maharashtra)"
    },{
      "question": "Who authored ancient Sanskrit plays 'Malti Madhava', 'Mahavircharita' and 'Uttar Ramcharita' ? ",
    "a":"Kalidas",
    "b": "Bhavabhuti",
    "c": "Banabhatta",
    "d": "Vishakhadatta",
    "answer":"Bhavabhuti"
    },{
    "question": "For the first time, Cricket has been included in Asian Games to be held in 2010. Which format ? ",
    "a": "Twenty-20",
    "b":  "One Day Intl. (ODI)",
    "c":   "Test Match",
    "d":   "both Twenty-20  One day Intl. (ODI)",
    "answer":"Twenty-20"
    },{
     "question": "Nagarjunasagar Dam in Andhra Pradesh is built across which river ? ",
    "a": "Krishna",
    "b":  "Kaveri",
    "c": "Mahanadi",
    "d":"Godavari",
    "answer":"Krishna"
    },{
     "question": "Which country is also known as the 'Rainbow Nation' ? ",
    "a": "Australia",
    "b": "United Kingdom",
    "c":  "Switzerland",
    "d":  "South Africa",
     "answer":  "South Africa"
    },{
     "question": "In which city would you come across Sidi Bashir Mosque, famous for its Shaking Minarets (Jhulta Minar) ? ",
    "a": "Agra (Uttar Pradesh)",
    "b":  "Ahmedabad (Gujarat)",
    "c": "Hyderabad (Andhra Pradesh)",
    "d":  "Srinagar (Jammu  Kashmir)",
    "answer": "Ahmedabad (Gujarat)"
    },{
      "question": "The weapon based Dravidian martial art 'Silambam' is native of which south Indian state ? ",
    "a": "Kerala",
    "b":  "Tamil Nadu",
    "c":  "Karnataka",
    "d":  "Andhra Pradesh",
    "answer": "Tamil Nadu"
    },{
       "question": "Who is generally considered as the inventor of the 'Periodic Table', a tabular method of displaying the chemical elements ? ",
    "a":  "Gregor Mendel",
    "b":  "James Chadwick",
    "c":  "Dmitri Mendeleev",
    "d":  "Ernest Rutherford",
    "answer": "Dmitri Mendeleev"
    },{
       "question": "Which Indian lady writer authored Onasis award winning play 'Harvest', highlighting the controversial issue of organ trading in poverty-stricken areas ? ",
    "a":  "Kiran Desai",
    "b":  "Jhumpa Lahiri",
    "c":  "Manjula Padmanabhan",
    "d":"Arundhati Roy",
    "answer":"Manjula Padmanabhan"
    },{
       "question": "Which mineral is found at Aluva and Chavara in Kerala, Manavalakurichi in Tamil Nadu and Chatrapur in Orissa ? ",
    "a": "Copper",
    "b":   "Lignite",
    "c":  "Bauxite",
    "d":  "Thorium",
    "answer":"Thorium"
    },{
     "question": "Who was the first person to calculate the height of the Mount Everest ? ",
    "a":  "Andrew Waugh",
    "b":  "George Everest",
    "c":   "Nain Singh Rawat",
    "d":  "Radhanath Sikdar",
    "answer": "Radhanath Sikdar"
    },{
      "question": "Which African country was formerly known as 'Abyssinia' ? ",
    "a":  "Namibia",
    "b":   "Lesotho",
    "c":   "Ethiopia",
    "d":   "Botswana",
      "answer":  "Ethiopia"
        }, {
       "question": "What is the popular name of Magnesium Sulphate, a white crystalline salt used in medicine and in leather processing ? ",
    "a": "Common salt",
    "b": "Epsom salt",
    "c":  "Baking soda",
    "d":  "Caustic soda",
      "answer": "Epsom salt"
    },{
         "question": "To whom does the Vice President of India address his resignation ? ",
    "a": "President",
    "b":   "Prime Minister",
    "c":  "Rajya Sabha Deputy Speaker",
    "d":  "Lok Sabha Speaker",
    "answer":"President"
    },{
     "question": "Paradip port, a major port on the Bay of Bengal, is located in which Indian state ? ",
    "a":"Orissa",
    "b":  "West Bengal",
    "c":  "Tamil Nadu",
    "d": "Andhra Pradesh",
     "answer": "Orissa"
    },{
    "question": "What discovery was made by biologist duo James D. Watson (US) and Francis Crick (UK) in 1953 ? ",
    "a":   "Penicillin",
    "b":   "DNA structure",
    "c":   "Synthetic Antigens",
    "d":  "Malaria germs",
      "answer":  "DNA structure"
    },{
      "question": "Under Annapurna Scheme by Central Government, how much food grain (wheat or rice) per month is given free to senior citizens (65 years or above age), who though eligible but remained uncovered under the National Old Age Pension Scheme (NOAPS)?",
    "a":  "10 Kgs",
    "b":  "12 Kgs",
    "c": "15 Kgs",
    "d":  "20 Kgs",
      "answer":  "10 Kgs"
    },{
     "question": "The Ilbert Bill, by which Indian judges were allowed to try the European offenders in criminal cases, was introduced by which Governor-General of India in 1883 ? ",
    "a":  "Lord Mayo",
    "b":  "Lord Irwin",
    "c": "Lord Rippon",
    "d":  "Lord Curzon",
     "answer":  "Lord Rippon"
        }, {
         "question": "Which among the following is manufactured at Avadi (abbreviation for 'Armoured Vehicles and Ammunition Depot of India') town in Tamilnadu ? ",
    "a":  "Maruti Cars",
    "b":  "HMT Tractors",
    "c":  "Tejas Aircrafts",
    "d": "Arjun Tanks",
     "answer": "Arjun Tanks"
        }, {
       "question": "Which US city is popularly known as the 'City of the Golden Gate' ? ",
    "a": "New York",
    "b":  "Washington",
    "c":  "San Francisco",
    "d":  "Los Angeles",
    "answer":  "San Francisco"
    },{
       "question": "Which Nobel laureate authored the novel 'A House for Mr. Biswas' ? ",
    "a": "Amartya Sen",
    "b":  "Rudyard Kipling",
    "c": "V.S. Naipaul",
    "d": "Rabindranath Tagore",
    "answer": "V.S. Naipaul"
    },{
       "question": "Where was the 'Project Tiger', the tiger protection programme, launched on 1 April 1973 ? ",
    "a": "Simlipal National Park (Orissa)",
    "b":  "Kanha National Park (Madhya Pradesh)",
    "c":  "Ranthambhore National Park (Rajasthan)",
    "d":   "Corbett National Park (Uttarakhand)",
      "answer":  "Corbett National Park (Uttarakhand)"
        }, {
        "question": "'Zindagi Ka Karvan' book is an autobiography of which former Prime Minister of India ? ",
    "a":"Chandrashekhar",
    "b":   "Morarji Desai",
    "c":   "Atal Bihari Vajpayee",
    "d":   "Vishwanath Pratap Singh",
    "answer":"Chandrashekhar"
    },{
        "question": "Which Indian state was originally known as the North East Frontier Agency (NEFA) ? ",
    "a":  "Manipur",
    "b":  "Meghalaya",
    "c":   "Arunachal Pradesh",
    "d":  "Nagaland",
            "answer":   "Arunachal Pradesh"
        }, {
        "question": "Which among the following instrument is used for maesuring wind speed ? ",
    "a":  "Anemometer",
    "b":   "Hygrometer",
    "c":   "Galvanometer",
    "d":   "Spectrometer",
     "answer":  "Anemometer"
        }, {
    "question": "Which strait connects the Pacific Ocean to the Atlantic Ocean ? ",
    "a":  "Strait of Malacca",
     "b": "Strait of Magellan",
    "c":  "Strait of Gibraltar",
    "d":  "Strait of Hormuz",
     "answer":  "Strait of Magellan"
        }, {
     "question": "Which national film award is given to the 'Best Feature Film on National Integration' ? ",
    "a": "Indira Gandhi Award",
    "b":  "Nargis Dutt Award",
    "c":  "Swarna Kamal (Golden Lotus)",
    "d":   "Rajat Kamal (Silver Lotus)",
            "answer":  "Nargis Dutt Award"
        },{
        "question": "Which coastal town in Gujarat is world famous for its ship-breaking industry ? ",         
        "a": "Okha",
        "b":  "Kandla",
        "c":  "Alang",
        "d":  "Veraval",
        "answer":"Alang"
        },{
           "question": "In which sport do sportswoman Jhulan Goswami, Mithali Raj, Anjum Chopra, Rumeli Dhar and Amita Sharma represent India ? ",
        "a": "Hockey",
        "b": "Tennis",
        "c": "Badminton",
        "d":  "Cricket",
         "answer":"Cricket" 
            }, {
         "question": "In the Earth's crust, which chemical element has the largest share of 47 percent in terms of weight ? ",
        "a": "Iron",
        "b":   "Silicon",
        "c":  "Oxygen",
        "d":  "Aluminium",
          "answer": "Oxygen"
            }, {
        "question": "In which battle, fought near the banks of Chenab river, did the British Army decisively defeat Sikh Army and annex the Sikh Kingdom of the Punjab to the British Empire ? ",
         "a":  "Battle of Buxar (1764)",
        "b":  "Battle of Plassey (1757)",
        "c":  "Battle of Surat (1664)",
        "d":   "Battle of Gujarat (1849)",
          "answer":  "Battle of Gujarat (1849)"
            }, {
              "question": "Which Ramon Magsaysay Award winner, popularly known as Water Man, founded an NGO called 'Tarun Bharat Sangh' near Alwar in Rajasthan to work on watershed projects  rain-water harvesting ? ",
        "a": "Sandeep Pandey",
        "b":  "Rajendra Singh",
        "c":  "Mahesh Chandra Mehta",
        "d":  "Arvind Kejriwal",
         "answer":  "Rajendra Singh"
            }, {
           "question": "In addition to main Bombay Bench, where are the three other benches of Bombay High Court located ? ",
        "a": "Pune, Nasik and Aurangabad",
        "b": "Panaji (Goa), Pune and Nagpur",
        "c":  "Aurangabad, Nagpur and Pune",
        "d":  "Panaji (Goa), Aurangabad and Nagpur",
          "answer": "Panaji (Goa), Aurangabad and Nagpur"
            }, {
         "question": "What name is given to the study or collection of money, coins or often medals ? ",
        "a":  "Lotology",
        "b":  "Philately",
        "c":  "Numismatics",
        "d":  "Philography",
         "answer":   "Numismatics"
            }, {
          
           "question": "Which among the following is not a part of the 'Triathlon', an athletic event combining three sporting events ? ",
        "a": "Running",
        "b":   "Cycling",
        "c":  "Long Jump",
        "d":   "Swimming",
            "answer": "Long Jump"
            }, {
        "question": "'Bandar Seri Begawan' is the capital city of which Asian country ? ",
        "a":  "Laos",
        "b":   "Brunei",
        "c":   "Vietnam",
        "d":   "Taiwan",
           "answer":  "Brunei"
            }, {
          "question": "Which among the following chemical is used in photography ? ",
        "a":  "Copper sulphate",
        "b":   "Silver bromide",
        "c":  "Calcium carbide",
        "d":"Calcium sulphate",
           "answer":   "Silver bromide"
            }, {
          "question": "In which city is the Central Institute for Research on Buffaloes located ? ",
        "a": "Hisar (Haryana)",
        "b": "Mathura (Uttar Pradesh)",
        "c": "Bikaner (Rajasthan)",
        "d":  "Dirang (Arunachal Pradesh)",
        "answer":  "Hisar (Haryana)"
            }, {
             "question": "On 1 April 1954, who became the first Indian Chief of the Indian Air Force (IAF) ? ",
        "a": "P.C. Lal",
        "b":   "Arjan Singh",
        "c":   "S. Mukherjee",
        "d":  "A.M. Engineer",
           "answer":"S. Mukherjee" 
            }, {
            "question": "In which Indian state, do the people of the Gaddis tribe live ? ",
        "a": "Himachal Pradesh",
        "b":   "West Bengal",
        "c":   "Arunachal Pradesh",
        "d":   "Andaman  Nicobar Islands",
          "answer":"Himachal Pradesh"
            }, {
          "question": "Which Indian tennis player duo, the first men's doubles pair to reach the finals of all four Grand Slam tennis tournaments in Open era, is popularly called 'Indian Express' ? ",
        "a": "Vijay Amritraj  Anand Amritraj",
        "b": "Jaideep Mukherjee  Premjit Lall",
        "c":   "Ramesh Krishnan  Zeeshan Ali",
        "d":  "Mahesh Bhupathi  Leander Paes",
          "answer": "Mahesh Bhupathi  Leander Paes"
            }, {
          "question": "Which lady freedom fighter, who once served as Congress president, authored collection of poems 'The Golden Threshold', 'The Bird of Time' and 'The Broken Wing' ? ",
        "a": "Annie Besant",
        "b":  "Indira Gandhi",
        "c":   "Nellie Sengupta",
        "d": "Sarojini Naidu",
          "answer":"Sarojini Naidu" 
            }, {
          "question": "Every year on Kartik Purnima, which town hosts India's biggest camel fair ? ",
        "a": "Sonepur (Bihar)",
        "b":   "Pushkar (Rajasthan)",
        "c":  "Surajkund (Haryana)",
        "d":  "Madhavpur (Gujarat)",
         "answer": "Pushkar (Rajasthan)"
            }, {
          "question": "At which session was the Indian National Congress (INC) divided into two groups - 'Naram Dal' (the moderates) and 'Garam Dal' (the extremists) ? ",
        "a": "Surat (1907)",
        "b":  "Gaya (1922)",
        "c": "Lahore (1929)",
        "d":  "Tripuri (1939)",
         "answer":  "Surat (1907)"
            }, {
         "question": "Kaziranga National Park, famous for hosting two-thirds of world's Indian Rhinoceroses (Great One-horned Rhinoceroses), is located in which Indian state ? ",
         "a":  "Assam",
        "b": "Meghalaya",
        "c":  "Manipur",
        "d": "West Bengal",
          "answer":  "Assam"
            }, {
            "question": "Which among the following was invented by Orville and Wilbur Wright, popularly known as Wright brothers, in 1903 ? ",
        "a":  "Submarine",
        "b": "Hovercraft",
        "c": "Helicopter",
        "d":  "Aeroplane",
           "answer": "Aeroplane"
            }, {
             "question": "'Playground of Europe' is the nickname of which European country ? ",
        "a": "Greece",
        "b":   "Monaco",
        "c":  "Germany",
        "d": "Switzerland",
        "answer":  "Switzerland"
            }, {
          "question": "Which city hosted the first Asian Games in 1951 ? ",
         "a":   "Tokyo (Japan)",
        "b":    "Jakarta (Indonesia)",
        "c":  "New Delhi (India)",
        "d":   "Manila (Philippines)",
        "answer":"Jakarta (Indonesia)"
            }, {
          "question": "Ukai Dam, located near Surat in Gujarat, is built across which river ? ",
        "a": "Mahi",
        "b":  "Tapti",
        "c":  "Narmada",
        "d": "Sabarmati",
          "answer":  "Tapti"
            }, {
            "question": "Which among the following are major constituents of Liquefied Petroleum Gas (LPG) ? ",
        "a": "Ethane and Methane",
        "b":  "Carbon monoxide and Hydrogen",
        "c":  "Butane and Propane",
        "d":  "Carbon monoxide, Hydrogen and Methane",
         "answer":  "Butane and Propane"
            }, {
              "question": "Which city in Uttar Pradesh is famous for Glass Bangles industry ?",
            "a": "Agra",
            "b":  "Firozabad",
            "c":  "Moradabad",
            "d":   "Aligarh",
               "answer":  "Firozabad"
                }, {
               "question": "In humans, how many chromosomes does a cell have ?",
            "a": "42 (21 pairs)",
            "b":   "44 (22 pairs)",
            "c":   "46 (23 pairs)",
            "d":   "48 (24 pairs)",
             "answer":  "46 (23 pairs)"
                }, {
             "question": "Who was popularly known as the 'Iron Man of India' ?",
            "a":"Bhagat Singh",
            "b": "Chandrashekhar Azad",
            "c":  "Veer Savarkar",
            "d":  "Vallabhbhai Patel",
             "answer":  "Vallabhbhai Patel"
                }, {
              "question": "During the reign of which ancient Indian ruler, did Chinese traveller Fa-Hien visit India ?",
            "a": "Dharmapala",
            "b": "Harshavardhan",
            "c": "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "d": "Chandragupta Vikramaditya",
             "answer": "Chandragupta Vikramaditya"
                }, {
              "question": "By what name is spiritual guru Narendra Nath Datta, founder of Belur Math near Kolkata, better known ?",
            "a": "Swami Vivekanand",
            "b":  "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "c":   "Swami Prabhupad",
            "d":   "Ramkrishna Paramahamsa",
              "answer": "Swami Vivekanand"
                }, {
             "question": "'Uhuru Peak' at Mount Kilimanjaro is the highest point of which continent ?",
            "a":"Asia",
            "b": "Africa",
            "c": "South America",
            "d": "Antarctica",
             "answer":  "Africa"
                }, {
              "question": "Millennium Dome, where Priyanka Chopra was crowned Miss World in 2000, is located in which European city ?",
            "a": "Paris (France)",
            "b":  "London (UK)",
            "c": "Moscow (Russia)",
            "d":   "Rome (Italy)",
             "answer":  "London (UK)"
                }, {
             "question": "Soft toy 'Teddy Bear' was named after which US president's nickname ?",
            "a": "Abraham Lincoln",
            "b": "George Washington",
            "c":  "Theodore Roosevelt",
            "d":  "John F. Kennedy",
             "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
                }, {
             "question": "In February 2009, which Indian music maestro won the Grammy Award for his collaborative music album 'Golden Drum Project' ?",
            "a":  "Zakir Hussain",
            "b":  "Pt. Shiv Kumar Sharma",
            "c":  "Pt. Ravi Shankar",
            "d":  "Amjad Ali Khan",
             "answer":  "Zakir Hussain"
                }, {
             "question": "Out of five Stree Shakti Puraskar, one is named after a fictional character of Tamil epic 'Silappatikaram'. Which one among the following four ?",
            "a":"Mata Jijabai",
            "b": "Rani Gaidenlou Zeliang",
            "c": "Devi Ahilya Bai Holkar",
            "d": "Kannagi",
             "answer": "Kannagi" 
                }, {
              "question": "Which is the only bird that can fly backwards ? ",
            "a": "Sunbird",
            "b": "Kingfisher",
            "c":  "Honeyeater",
            "d":  "Hummingbird",
              "answer": "Hummingbird"
                }, {
             "question": "'Chanderi' and 'Maheshwari' sarees are native of which state ? ",
            "a":"Tamil Nadu",
            "b":  "West Bengal",
            "c":  "Madhya Pradesh",
            "d":  "Maharashtra",
              "answer": "Madhya Pradesh"
                }, {
             "question": "Quinine, the anti-malaria drug, is made from the bark of which tree ? ",
            "a":"Cinchona",
            "b":  "Wintergreen",
            "c":  "Peppermint",
            "d":  "Eucalyptus",
              "answer": "Cinchona"
                }, {
             "question": "Titan, the only moon (natural satellite) known to have a dense atmosphere, is the largest moon of which planet ? ",
            "a": "Mars",
            "b":  "Jupiter",
            "c": "Saturn",
            "d":  "Uranus",
             "answer": "Saturn"
                }, {
             "question": "Which dynasty, founded by Mauryan senapati (commander-in-chief) Pushyamitra, was immediate successor of the Maurya dyanasty ? ",
            "a": "Gupta dynasty",
            "b": "Kanva dynasty",
            "c": "Nanda dynasty",
            "d": "Shunga dynasty",
             "answer": "Shunga dynasty"
                }, {
             "question": "Which coastal city is known as the 'Queen of the Arabian Sea' ? ",
            "a": "Kochi (Kerala)",
            "b":  "Mangalore (Karnataka)",
            "c":   "Ratnagiri (Maharashtra)",
            "d":   "Marmagao (Goa)",
             "answer":  "Kochi (Kerala)"
                }, {
               "question": "On 1 September 1939, attack on which country by Germany marked the start of World War II ? ",
            "a": "France",
            "b":  "Poland",
            "c":   "Britain",
            "d":  "Belgium",
             "answer": "Poland"
                }, {
             "question": "In 1981, which Mumbai born British writer won the Booker Prize for his novel 'Midnight's Children' ? ",
            "a": "Salman Rushdie",
            "b":  "V.S.Naipaul",
            "c":   "Arundhati Roy",
            "d":   "Kiran Desai",
            "answer":  "Salman Rushdie"
                }, {
             "question": "In 1913, at which American city did Lala Har Dayal found the 'Ghadar Party' ? ",
            "a": "Boston",
            "b": "California",
            "c": "Philadelphia",
            "d": "San Francisco",
               "answer":   "San Francisco"
                }, {
             "question": "By voter strength, which Indian parliamentary constituency (Lok Sabha seat) having more than 33 lakh voters holds the world record of the largest constituency ? ",
            "a":"Chandni Chowk (Delhi)",
            "b":  "Outer Delhi (Delhi)",
            "c": "Nandyal (Andhra Pradesh)",
            "d":  "Samastipur (Bihar)",
               "answer":"Outer Delhi (Delhi)" 
                }, {
             "question": "What name has been given to the first Boeing 747/700 jet, inducted into Indian Air Force, designed to work as the Indian President's office-in-the-sky ? ",
            "a": "Samrat",
            "b":  "Rajdoot",
            "c": "Maharaja",
            "d":  "Badshah",
              "answer":  "Rajdoot"
                }, {
             "question": "Which pigment gives plants and leaves their green colour ? ",
            "a": "Betalain",
            "b": "Chlorophyll",
            "c": "Carotenoid",
            "d":  "Anthocyanin",
              "answer":  "Chlorophyll"
                }, {
             "question": "As a token of protest against Jallianwala Bagh massacre on 13 April 1919, who returned the Knighthood conferred on him by the British Government ? ",
            "a": "Rabindranath Tagore",
            "b": "Tej Bahadur Sapru",
            "c": "Gopal Krishna Gokhle",
            "d":  "Syed Ahmed Khan",
             "answer":  "Rabindranath Tagore"
                }, {
              "question": "On 6 Apr 2009, which Indian cricketer surpassed Australian Mark Waugh's world record for the most catches in Test Cricket by a fielder (excluding wicket-keeper) ? ",
            "a": "Sunil Gavaskar",
            "b": "V.V.S.Laxman",
            "c":  "Rahul Dravid",
            "d": "Mohammed Azharuddin",
              "answer":  "Rahul Dravid"
                }, {
             "question": "What is the retirement age of High Court judges ? ",
            "a":"60 years",
            "b": "62 years",
            "c": "65 years",
            "d": "70 years",
             "answer": "62 years"
                }, {
             "question": "Which apparatus is used to measure the blood pressure ? ",
            "a": "Hygrometer",
            "b":  "Chronometer",
            "c":  "Thermometer",
            "d":  "Sphygmomanometer",
             "answer": "Sphygmomanometer"
                }, {
             "question": "Which renowned dancer established classical dance school 'Kalakshetra' at Adyar near Chennai in 1931 ? ",
            "a": "Protima Gauri Bedi",
            "b":   "Sonal Mansingh",
            "c":  "Mrinalini Sarabhai",
            "d": "Rukmini Devi Arundale",
              "answer":  "Rukmini Devi Arundale"
                }, {
             "question": "Kudremukh hills, name literally meaning Horse face, in Karnataka are famous for mines of which mineral ? ",
            "a": "Gold",
            "b":  "Lignite",
            "c":  "Bauxite",
            "d": "Iron Ore",
             "answer":  "Iron Ore"
                }, {
              "question": "Ghatigaon Sanctuary, set up for the conservation of the Son Chiriya (great Indian bustard), is located in which state ? ",
            "a": "Haryana",
            "b":  "Rajasthan",
            "c":   "Madhya Pradesh",
            "d":  "Karnataka",
            "answer": "Madhya Pradesh"
                }, {
             "question": "The novel 'Q  A', on which 8 Oscar awards winning film 'Slumdog Millionaire' (2008) is based, was authored by which Indian civil servant ? ",
            "a": "Vikas Swarup",
            "b": "Vikram Seth",
            "c":   "Amitav Ghosh",
            "d": "Aravind Adiga",
                    "answer": "Vikas Swarup" 
                }, {
             "question": "Which hormone, released when danger threatens, is known as Emergency hormone ? ",
            "a": "Insulin",
            "b":  "Adrenaline",
            "c":  "Melatonin",
            "d": "Thyroxine",
              "answer":  "Adrenaline"
                }, {
            "question": "'Kathakali', 'Mohiniaattam' and 'Thullal' dance forms are native of which state ? ",
            "a": "Karnataka",
            "b":  "Andhra Pradesh",
            "c": "Tamil Nadu",
            "d": "Kerala",
            "answer":  "Kerala"
                }, {
              "question": "Which is the only continent through which all longitude lines passes ? ",
            "a": "Asia",
            "b":   "Africa",
            "c":  "Antarctica",
            "d":  "Australia",
              "answer":  "Antarctica"
                }, {
             "question": "'Vinaya Pitaka', 'Sutta Pitaka' and 'Abhidhamma Pitaka' - collectively known as the 'Tripitaka' (three baskets) - are sacred texts of which religion ? ",
            "a": "Jainism",
            "b": "Sikhism",
            "c":  "Buddhism",
            "d":   "Christianity",
             "answer": "Buddhism"
                }, {
            "question": "In 1997, to which Indian film star did Pakistan Government present its highest civilian award 'Nishan-e-Intiaz' ? ",
            "a":"Dev Anand",
            "b":  "Raj Kapoor",
            "c": "Amitabh Bachchan",
            "d":  "Dilip Kumar",
              "answer": "Dilip Kumar"
                }, {
              "question": "On 18 March 1965, who became the first human to walk in the space ? ",
            "a": "Yuri Gagarin",
            "b":  "Alexey Leonov",
            "c": "Neil Armstrong",
            "d":   "Buzz Aldrin",
              "answer": "Alexey Leonov"
                }, {
             "question": "Washington D.C., the capital of United States of America, is located on the banks of which river ? ",
            "a":"Seine",
            "b": "Thames",
            "c":  "Potomac",
            "d":  "Moskva",
              "answer":  "Potomac"
                }, {
             "question": "Which among the following is the first indigenous civilian aircraft of India ? ",
            "a":"Saras",
            "b":  "Tejas",
            "c":  "Chetak",
            "d": "Cheetah",
              "answer": "Saras"
                }, {
              "question": "Near which city is the Salim Ali Centre for Ornithology and Natural History located ? ",
            "a":"Panaji (Goa)",
            "b":"Coimbatore (Tamil Nadu)",
            "c": "Bharatpur (Rajasthan)",
            "d":  "Sultanpur (Haryana)",
             "answer": "Coimbatore (Tamil Nadu)"
                }, {
             "question": "Which Central American country was formerly known as 'British Honduras' ? ",
            "a":"Belize",
            "b":"Malawi",
            "c": "Botswana",
            "d":  "Benin",
              "answer": "Belize"
                }, {
            "question": "What is the minimum age limit to become the Governor of a state in India ? ",
            "a":  "18 years",
            "b": "25 years",
            "c": "30 years",
            "d":   "35 years",
             "answer": "35 years"
                }, {
             "question": "Yakshagana, literally meaning celestial music, is a popular dance drama of which Indian state ? ",
            "a": "Gujarat",
            "b":  "Maharashtra",
            "c":  "Karnataka",
            "d":  "West Bengal",
              "answer": "Karnataka" 
                }, {
             "question": "Hirakud Dam at Sambalpur in Orissa, the longest dam in India, is built across which river ? ",
            "a": "Narmada",
            "b":  "Mahanadi",
            "c":  "Godavari",
            "d": "Kaveri",
            "answer": "Mahanadi"
                }, {
             "question": "Among terrestrial (land) animals, which animal has the longest gestation period ? ",
            "a":"Tiger",
            "b":  "Elephant",
            "c":  "Rhinoceros",
            "d":  "Horse",
              "answer":  "Elephant"
                }, {
              "question": "For writing the Punjabi language, which Sikh guru developed the Gurumukhi script ? ",
            "a": "Guru Angad",
            "b": "Guru Amar Das",
            "c":  "Guru Ram Das",
            "d":  "Guru Arjan",
              "answer":  "Guru Angad"
                }, {
               "question": "Which among the following disease is caused by female Aedes Aegypti mosquitoes ? ",
            "a": "Malaria",
            "b": "Kala-Azar",
            "c": "Dengue Fever",
            "d": "Typhoid",
             "answer":  "Dengue Fever"
                }, {
               "question": "'Mein Kampf' (My Struggle) book is the autobiography of which dictator ? ",
            "a":"Pol Pot",
            "b":"Idi Amin",
            "c":  "Adolf Hitler",
             "d": "Joseph Stalin",
             "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
                }, {
              "question": "Who was the chief guest at the Republic Day celebrations on 26th January 2009 in New Delhi ? ",
            "a":  "Vladimir Putin (Russian President)",
            "b":  "Nicolas Sarkozy (French President)",
            "c":  "Zigme Singye Wangchuk (Bhutan King)",
            "d":  "Nursultan Nazarbayev (Kazakhstan President)",
             "answer":  "Nursultan Nazarbayev (Kazakhstan President)"
                }, {
             "question": "In 1916, who founded Shreemati Nathibai Damodar Thackersey (SNDT) Women's University at Pune, the first women's university in India ? ",
            "a":"Annie Besant",
            "b": "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "c": "Madan Mohan Malaviya",
            "d":  "Dhondo Keshav Karve",
             "answer": "Dhondo Keshav Karve"
                }, {
              "question": "In which African city are the headquarters of United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP) located ? ",
            "a": "Nairobi (Kenya)",
            "b":   "Cairo (Egypt)",
            "c":    "Abuja (Nigeria)",
            "d":   "Addis Ababa (Ethiopia)",
              "answer":  "Nairobi (Kenya)"
                }, {
               "question": "Which natural sugar is found in the milk ?",
            "a": "Lactose",
            "b":   "Sucrose",
            "c":   "Maltose",
            "d":  "Fructose",
               "answer":  "Lactose"
                }, { 
               "question": "'Nepali', 'Lepcha', 'Bhutia' and 'Limbu' are the main spoken langauges of which Indian state ?",
            "a": "Manipur",
            "b": "Mizoram",
            "c":  "Sikkim",
            "d":  "Nagaland",
             "answer": "Sikkim"
                }, {
               "question": "On 15 May 1952, who became the first speaker of the Lok Sabha ?",
            "a": "Sukumar Sen",
            "b":  "G.V.Mavalankar",
            "c":  "Harilal J. Kania",
            "d": "S.Radhakrishnan",
             "answer":  "G.V.Mavalankar"
                }, {
             "question": "Which royal poet of Delhi Sultanate is regarded as the 'Father of Qawwali' ?",
            "a": "Tansen",
            "b":  "Baiju Bawra",
            "c":  "Nayak Charju",
            "d":  "Amir Khusro",
               "answer":  "Amir Khusro"
                }, {
               "question": "In 1976, which Bengali lady novelist became the first woman to receive the Jnanpith Award for her novel 'Pratham Pritisruti' (First Promise) ?",
            "a":  "Ashapurna Devi",
            "b":  "Mahasveta Devi",
            "c":  "Mahadevi Varma",
            "d":  "Amrita Pritam",
               "answer":   "Ashapurna Devi"
                }, {
              "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution gives special status to Jammu and Kashmir ?",
            "a": "Article 352",
            "b":  "Article 356",
            "c": "Article 360",
            "d": "Article 370",
             "answer":"Article 370" 
                }, {
             "question": "Immortalized in the voice of Lata Mangeshkar, Kavi Pradeep's famous patriotic song 'Aye mere watan ke logon' was set to music by which musician ?",
            "a":"Naushad",
            "b": "S.D.Burman",
            "c":  "O.P.Nayyar",
            "d":  "C.Ramchandra",
             "answer": "C.Ramchandra"
                }, {
             "question": "Coined by French priest Henri Didon, 'Citius, Altius, Fortius' (Swifter, Higher, Stronger) slogan is the motto of which tournament ?",
            "a":"Olympic Games",
            "b":  "Commonwealth Games",
            "c":  "FIFA World Cup",
            "d": "Asian Games",
            "answer": "Olympic Games"
                }, {
            "question": "Who was popularly known as the 'Lady with the Lamp' ?",
            "a": "Mother Teresa",
            "b": "Sister Nivedita",
            "c": "Florence Nightingale",
            "d":  "The Mother (Mirra Alfassa)",
             "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
                }, {
             "question": "Falkland Islands, located in South Atlantic Ocean, are a self-governing Overseas Territory of which country ?",
            "a": "France",
            "b":  "United Kingdom",
            "c":  "Argentina",
            "d":  "Spain",
             "answer": "United Kingdom"
                }, {
              "question": "On 1st July 1997, where was India's first Science City inaugurated ? ",
            "a":"Mumbai",
            "b": "Bengaluru",
            "c": "Hyderabad",
            "d": "Kolkata",
              "answer": "Kolkata"
                }, {
             "question": "What is the name of Morarji Desai's samadhi in Ahmedabad ? ",
            "a": "Raj Ghat",
            "b": "Vijay Ghat",
            "c": "Abhay Ghat",
            "d":"Narayan Ghat",
             "answer": "Abhay Ghat"
                }, {
              "question": "In 1829, which Governor-General prohibited the practice of 'Sati' ? ",
            "a": "Lord Auckland",
            "b":  "Lord Amherst",
            "c":  "Lord William Bentinck",
            "d":  "Lord Dalhousie",
             "answer":   "Lord William Bentinck"
                }, {
             "question": "Who authored the book 'Indica' ? ",
            "a": "Fa Hian",
            "b": "Megasthanese",
            "c":  "Al Beruni",
            "d": "Huen Tsang",
              "answer":  "Megasthanese"
                }, {
                "question": "Which is the oldest stock exchange in Asia ? ",
            "a": "Tokyo Stock Exchange",
            "b":  "Hong Kong Stock Exchange",
            "c":  "Shanghai Stock Exchange",
            "d":  "Bombay Stock Exchange",
            "answer": "Bombay Stock Exchange"
                }, {
             "question": "Who is the chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission of India ? ",
            "a":"Mangala Rai",
            "b":   "Sam Pitroda",
            "c":   "Anil Kakodkar",
            "d":  "G.Madhavan Nair",
               "answer":  "Anil Kakodkar"
                }, {
            "question": "By defeating Harshavardhana on the banks of river Narmada, which Chalukya ruler stopped him from expanding into south ? ",
            "a":"Pulkesin I",
            "b": "Pulkesin II",
            "c": "Vinayaditya",
            "d": "Vijayaditya",
              "answer":  "Pulkesin II"
                }, {
             "question": "In 1892, who became the first Indian to be elected to the House of Commons (lower house of British Parliament) ? ",
            "a":"Mahatma Gandhi",
            "b": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "c":  "Tej Bahadur Sapru",
            "d":  "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
              "answer":  "Dadabhai Naoroji"
                }];
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    